Guide to the Records of Amnesty International of the USA, Inc.
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Amnesty International of the USA, Inc. National Office Records,
1966-2003
[Bulk Dates: 1974-1993]
Amnesty International USA. National Office.
107.52 linear feet (256 document boxes).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY. 10027
6093730
The records document the founding and development of Amnesty International of the USA, Inc. (AIUSA) and its national office. AIUSA is the largest national section of Amnesty International, an international human rights non-governmental organization (NGO). The records include material related to the board of directors, executive directors, administration, operations, campaigns, casework, publicity, special projects, and the work of the organization and its membership on human rights issues.
Historical Note
Amnesty International (AI), an international human rights non-governmental organization (NGO), was founded in London by Peter Benenson in 1961. Benenson, a lawyer, had become concerned about the case of two students imprisoned in Portugal for toasting to freedom in a bar. He published an article in the London Observer on the case on May 28, 1961, and advocated the writing of letters to the Portuguese government demanding the release of the students. The response was extraordinary. The article was translated and reprinted internationally, and readers began sending letters and support not only to Benenson, but also to prisons and labor camps worldwide.
In July 1961, an international group of delegates met and decided to establish "a permanent international movement in defense of freedom of opinion and religion." Shortly thereafter, an office and library was established in London, staffed by volunteers. Affiliated letter-writing groups were initially established in the United Kingdom, West Germany, Holland, France, Italy, and Switzerland, and expanded the following year to Norway, Sweden, Demark, Belgium, Greece, Australia, Ireland and the United States. By the end of 1962, 210 prisoners had been adopted by 70 groups in 7 countries, and Amnesty International had sent missions to Ghana, Czechoslovakia, Portugal and East Germany. By 1970, the organization had expanded to 850 groups in 27 countries.
As the organization grew, a Research Bureau and the International Secretariat -- the central office that serves as the headquarters of the international organization -- were formally established in London in 1963. That same year, the International Executive Committee (IEC), which has overall responsibility for AI's affairs, was established under the aegis of Sean MacBride, an Irish human rights advocate. National organizational structures, or sections, were also established to coordinate work within countries under the leadership of the headquarters in London. The United States section (known as Amnesty International of the USA, Inc. or AIUSA), the largest in the organization, was incorporated in 1966.
The National Office was the United States section's main professional office until approximately the early 1970s. Additional regional and program offices were established throughout the 1970s and early 1980s. Prior to 1981, the board of directors handled much of the daily administration of the section. After this time, the presence of an established professional structure allowed the board to focus more exclusively on policy issues. This expansion, professionalization, and a push for decentralization during the 1980s by allowed for the management of the section's work to expand beyond the National Office. The work of the section is carried out through the national office, regional offices, networks, country specialists (formerly known as country coordination groups or co-groups), student groups, and local groups. In addition, as the budget of the International Secretariat is financed by assessments on the national sections, AIUSA, as the largest section, provides a significant portion of the International Secretariat's budget.
In its early years, the main focus of Amnesty International's campaigns was to free prisoners of conscience. Within a short time, the organization's mandate expanded to include campaigning for prompt and fair trails for all political prisoners, to end extrajudicial executions and disappearances, and to abolish the death penalty, torture and other cruel treatment or punishment. The organization has always worked to bring perpetrators of these abuses to justice in accordance with international standards. Amnesty International was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize for its work in 1977.
Amnesty International underwent tremendous growth during the 1980s. By 1985, there were 3,433 groups in 50 countries, and over 500,000 members. The organization also used music concerts to raise its profile and the awareness of human rights issues. In 1986, AIUSA organized the Conspiracy of Hope Tour in the United States, which included U2, Sting, Peter Gabriel, Bryan Adams, Lou Reed, the Neville Brothers. In 1988, Amnesty International organized Human Rights Now! This tour, which coincided with the 40th anniversary of the United Nations' Universal Declaration of Human Rights, went to 19 cities in 15 countries and was broadcast live on Human Rights Day. By 1990, Amnesty International had 700,000 members and over 6,000 groups in 70 countries.
Today, Amnesty International has over 2 million members, supports and subscribers in over 150 countries.
Scope and Content
The Amnesty International of the USA, Inc: National Office Records document AIUSA's founding, development, administration, decision-making processes, finances, fundraising, and the work of the section and its membership on human rights issues. The records also document the working relationships of the national office and the membership, other offices, sections, and the International Secretariat. The records include case files, country files, testimony files, minutes, reports, correspondence and records related to regional and annual meetings, development, events, special projects, communications, membership, and the work of country specialists, networks, and local groups.
Coverage is not comprehensive. Although AIUSA was incorporated in 1966, the bulk of the office records cover the mid-1970s through 1993, the last year of the executive directorship of Jack Healey. Early AIUSA activity is best documented by the records of the Board of Directors and the Annual General Meetings.
The records of the National Office are not fully processed and available for use at this time. Processed material includes records related to Board of Directors, Executive Directors, Annual General Meetings, and Membership Coordination and Mobilization. The processed material is fully described in the finding aid.
Records that are not yet processed or available for research include records related to the communications department, the development unit, special projects, country specialists (co-groups), networks, campaigns, country files, case files, and the majority of records related to general administration and operations.
The section's primary organizational function does not include management of Amnesty International's international affairs. The archives of the International Secretariat are held by the International Institute of Social History in Amsterdam.
Arrangement
In eleven series:
Series I: Board of Directors’ Files, 1965-2003
Series II: Executive Director Files, 1967-1997
Series III: Annual General Meetings, 1967-1997
Series IV: Membership Mobilization, 1971-1995
Series V: Country Coordination Groups, 1978-1995
Series VI: Networks, 1975-1995
Series VII: Campaign and Country Files, 1972-1997
Series VIII: Closed Cases, 1974-1983
Series IX: Communications Department/Media Relations Files, 1973-1997
Series X: Development Unit/Special Projects Files, 1986-1994
Series XI: Administration and Operations, 1966-1996
Subjects
Amnesty International USA.; Amnesty International USA.--Board of Directors.; Healey, Jack.; Civil rights.; Fund raising.; Human rights.; Membership campaigns.; Social rights.; Students--Political activity.; Student movements.; Annual Reports; Correspondence; Minutes; Notebooks
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library Reading Room. Please consult the Rare Book and Manuscript Library for further information.
This collection has restrictions. Restrictions for boxes and folders are noted in the series descriptions and may also be found within the contents list.
Acquisition
Amnesty International; Deposit; 20006
The material was originally deposited at the University of Colorado at Boulder by Amnesty International USA's National Office in the 1990s.
- Series I: Board of Directors, 1965-2003
  The AIUSA Board of Directors oversees many larger organizational issues such as budgets, fundraising, staffing, development, and policy. The Board is also responsible for representing the section's membership and participating in the larger international movement.
  - Subseries I.1: Board Meetings, 1965-2003
    This series consists of agendas, minutes, and other meeting materials. The files include memoranda, press clippings, reports of the Executive Director, and reports and minutes of the board committees. The files also contain reports and updates on countries, missions, meetings, programs, finances, and other issues of interest to the Board of Directors. The series is arranged chronologically.
    - Meetings
      - 1965-1977, (17 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 1-17)
      - 1978 April 2-1980 September 6, (15 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-15)
      - 1980 December 6-1981 August 2, (9 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 1-9)
      - 1981 September 18-1982 December 5, (9 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 1-9)
      - 1982 December 3 - 1984 February 26, (10 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 1-10)
      - 1984 June 20 - 1986 February 16, (10 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 1-9)
      - 1986 February 14 September 21, (7 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 1-7)
      - 1986 September 19 - 1989 January 31, (10 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 1-10)
      - 1988 January 30-November 19, (9 Folders) (Box 9, Folder 1-9)
      - 1988 November 18-1989 May 7, (7 Folders) (Box 10, Folder 1-7)
      - 1989 May - September 17, (8 Folders) (Box 11, Folder 1-8)
      - 1989 November-1990 May, (7 Folders) (Box 12, Folder 1-7)
      - 1990 May-1992 February 2, (12 Folders) (Box 13, Folder 1-12)
      - 1992 January 31-1993 February 7, (11 Folders) (Box 14, Folder 1-11)
      - 1993 February 5 - June 24, (9 Folders) (Box 15, Folder 1-9)
      - 1993 June 23-1994 October 2, (11 Folders) (Box 16, Folder 1-10)
      - 1994 September 30-1996 January 28, (8 Folders) (Box 17, Folder 1-8)
      - 1996 September 28-1997 March 9, (8 Folders) (Box 18, Folder 1-8)
      - 1997 March 7 - September 28, (8 Folders) (Box 19, Folder 1-8)
      - 1997 September 26-28, (2 Folders) (Box 20, Folder 1-2)
      - 1998 January 9-11, (3 Folders) (Box 20, Folder 3-5)
      - 1998 March 19-22, (2 folders) (Box 20, Folder 6-7)
        [restricted until April 2008]
      - 1998 March 19-22 (Box 20, Folder 8)
        (Press Clippings)
      - 1998 June 26-28, (2 Folders) (Box 21, Folder 1-2)
        [restricted until July 2008]
      - 1998 September 25-27, (2 Folders) (Box 21, Folder 3-4)
        [restricted until October 2008]
      - 1999 January 29-31, (2 Folders) (Box 21, Folder 5-6)
        [restricted until February 2009]
      - 1999 January 29-31 (Box 22, Folder 1)
      - 1999 April 15-19 (Box 22, Folder 2)
        [restricted until May 2009]
      - 1999 April 15-19 (Box 22, Folder 3)
      - 1999 June 25-27, (2 Folders) (Box 22, Folder 4-6)
        [restricted until July 2009]
      - 1999 June 25-27 (Box 22, Folder 7)
      - 1999 September 24-26, (2 Folders) (Box 22, Folder 8-9)
        [restricted until October 2009]
      - 1999 September 24-26, (2 Folders) (Box 23, Folder 1-2)
      - 1999 September 24-26 (Box 23, Folder 3)
      - 1999 December 10-12, (3 Folders) (Box 23, Folder 4-6)
        [restricted until 2010]
      - 1999 December 10-13 (Box 23, Folder 7)
      - 2000 March 9-12, (2 Folders) (Box 23, Folder 8-9)
        [restricted until April 2010]
      - 2000 March 9-12 (Box 24, Folder 1)
      - 2000 March 9-12 (Box 24, Folder 2)
        (Press Clippings and Public Documents)
      - 2000 July 7-9, (3 Folders) (Box 24, Folder 3-5)
        [restricted until August 2010]
      - 2000 July 7-9 (Box 24, Folder 6)
      - 2000 September 22-25, (2 Folders) (Box 24, Folder 7-8)
        [restricted until October 2010]
      - 2001 January 26-29 (Box 24, Folder 9)
        [restricted until February 2011]
      - 2001 January 26-29 (Box 25, Folder 1)
      - 2001 January 26-29 (Box 25, Folder 2)
        (Public Documents)
      - 2002 April 18, (2 Folders) (Box 25, Folder 3-4)
        [restricted until May 2012]
      - 2002 July 12-14, (2 Folders) (Box 25, Folder 5-6)
        [restricted until August 2012]
      - 2002 July 12-14 (Box 25, Folder 7)
        (Public Documents and Press Clippings)
      - 2002 September 27-29, (2 Folders) (Box 25, Folder 8-9)
        [restricted until October 2012]
      - 2002 September 27-29 (Box 26, Folder 1)
      - 2003 January 24-26, (2 Folders) (Box 26, Folder 2-3)
        [restricted until February 2013]
      - 2003 April 3, (2 Folders) (Box 26, Folder 4-5)
        [restricted until May 2013]
      - 2003 April 3 (Box 26, Folder 6)
      - 2003 September 19-21 (Box 26, Folder 7-8)
        [restricted until October 2013]
      - 2003 September 19-21 (Box 27, Folder 1)
      - 2004 July 16-18, (2 Folders) (Box 27, Folder 2-4)
        [restricted until September 2014]
      - 2004 October 1-3, (2 Folders) (Box 27, Folder 5-6)
        [restricted until November 2014]
  - Subseries I.2 Board Committees, 1967-1994
    Comprised mainly of agendas, minutes and other meeting materials related to the main board committees, the bulk of the files are related to the meetings of the board's Executive Committee (1974-1993; Bulk 1974-1982). Much of this material includes minutes and reports also available in the meeting materials of the Board of Directors in Series 1: Board Meetings. There is some additional material related to task forces and other committees in the Series 3: Subject Files. The series is arranged alphabetically.
    - Administration Committee, 1988-1993, (4 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
    - Audit Committee, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Executive Committee
      - General, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Matters, 1986-1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Meetings
        - 1974 January-1976 October, (14 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 8-22)
        - 1976 November 22-1977 December 10, (10 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-10)
        - 1977 December 10-1978 October 21, (9 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 1-9)
        - 1978 December 6-1980 August 16, (15 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 1-15)
        - 1980 September 5-1982 August 6, (16 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 1-16)
        - 1982 December-1987, (5 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 1-5)
      - Conference Call, 1988 August 15 -1993, (7 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 6-13)
      - Reports to the Executive Committee / Executive Committee Matters, 1986-1991 (Box 6, Folder 14)
      - Summary of Policy Decisions 1971-1980 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Finance and Fundraising Committee, 1980-1981 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - International Committee
      - 1987-1994, (2 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 17-18)
      - Participlan, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Committee on International Development (CID), 1989 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Committee on Internships and Fellowships, 1990-1991 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Program Committee, 1989-1994 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Subseries I.3: International Councils and Committees, 1968-1995
    This series includes meeting materials related to the International Council Meetings (ICM) (1968-1995) and the International Executive Committee (IEC) (1967-1993). Files on the ICM include information on proposals, resolutions, working parties, participants, and decisions. The files include both meeting materials and later reports on the meeting's proceedings, decisions and implementation of decisions. The IEC files include material related to the IEC's standing committees. This series is arranged alphabetically by main topic.
    - International Council Meetings (ICM)
      - 1968-1979, (13 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 1-13)
      - 1979-1983, (8 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-8)
      - 1983 Resolutions--Staff Comments on the Implementation of, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - United States Resolutions, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - 1984-1987, (7 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 1-7)
      - 1987-1991, (7 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 1-7)
      - 1991, (2 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
      - Mandate Review Committee--Yokohama, Japan, 1991 August 31 - September 7 (Box 5, Folder 3)
        [restricted until June 2022]
      - Working Party D--Yokohama, Japan, 1991 August 31 - September 7 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - 1993, (3 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 5-7)
      - 1995 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - Delegation Selection Process, 1985-1992 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - International Executive Committee (IEC)
      - AIUSA Annual Reports and Statistics Questionnaires to, 1985-1993 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - Agenda Paper on the Role and Function of the ICM, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 1)
        [restricted until July 2018]
      - Biographies of the Members, circa 1970s, Undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - Correspondence, 1985-1993 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Meetings
        - 1967-1975, (7 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 4-11)
        - 1979 (Box 6, Folder 12)
          [restricted until January 2010]
        - 1980 (Box 6, Folder 13)
          [restricted until September 2010]
        - 1981 (Box 6, Folder 14)
          [restricted until February 2014]
        - 1983 (Box 6, Folder 15)
        - 1985 (Box 6, Folder 16)
          [restricted until May 2015]
  - Subseries I.4: Subject Files, 1975-1995
    Much of the material in this series is related to issues of administration and policy including board elections, board structure and functions, finance, sectional and international meetings, planning and development, and staff issues. The files also include correspondence and reports on activities, programs and other issues. This series is arranged alphabetically.
    - Agenda Setting, 1985-1992 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Amnesty International 1961-1991 30 Years Working for Human Rights - 30th Anniversary Packet, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Amnesty International's Name--Guidelines for the Use of, February 1993 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Amnesty International USA--Public Identification and Cooperation with Outside Groups, April 1992 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Amnesty Publications--Proposal for a New AIUSA Magazine, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Annual General Meeting (AGM), 1977-1987, (6 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 6-12)
    - Area Coordinators--Job Description, 1991 September 15 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Assessments on Amnesty Sections in Various Countries, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Audits, 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Awards to Board, 1993-1993 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Ballots, 1982-1993, (2 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
    - Board of Directors
      - Barber, James David
        - Articles By, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 1)
        - Correspondence, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 2)
        - Correspondence and Other Material, 1985-1986, (2 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
      - Board/Board Relations, 1986-1993 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Board/Staff Relations, 1987-1993 (Box 2, Folder f .6)
      - Chair's Correspondence, 1987-1991 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Chairperson's Reports, 1990-1993 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Consultant's Reports, 1981-1989 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Correspondence, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Henry, Charles P. III, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Job Description, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Members
        - 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 13)
        - Bio Sheets, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 14)
        - Bios and Curriculum Vitae, Late 1980s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 15)
        - Lists, 1980-1995 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - Nagengast, Carole--Articles, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - New Board Orientation, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - Orientation Manual, 18 August 1993 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Orientation Materials, 1990-1992 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Peer Evaluation and Self Assessment [Forms], 1990-1992 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Reports from International Meetings [by Board Members], 1984-1993 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Streamlining Board Processes, 1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Structure and Function Task Force
        - 1991-June 1993, (3 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 6-8)
        - Undated. (Box 3, Folder 9)
        - Background Materials, 1986-1990 (Box 3, Folder 10)
        - Report, circa 1988 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Budget and Planning Reports FY 1994 1993 April-June, Undated, (2 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 12-13)
    - Buildings and Other Acquisitions (Washington DC Office), 1985-1989 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Bunche Fellowship, 1989-1993 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - By-Laws and Annual General Meeting (AGM) Standing Rules Committee, 1987-1989 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Calendar of Events, 1991-1993 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Campaign '88 Task Force, 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Case Work, 1988-1993 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Charter Committee on AIUSA Action methods (CAAM), 1991 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      (Also known as SYSTEC)
    - Co-Groups, 1989-1993 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Code of Conduct, 1990 September 4 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - College Task Force, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Committee on International Development (CID), 1987-1992 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Communications Program / Communications Department, 1987-1993 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Danish Doctors' Tour on Behalf of AI Medical Project, 1978 January-February (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Death Penalty--Proposals, 1991-1992 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Death Penalty--Reports, 1986-1992 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Decision Making/Strategic Planning, 1981-1993, Undated, (2 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 16-17)
      (including the Committee on Long-Term Organizational Development (CLOD))
    - Democratization Resolutions of the 1983 Annual General Meeting (AGM)--Legal Opinion on, 1983-1985 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Direct Mail, 1988-1992 (Box 4, Folder f .19)
    - Elections
      - 1981-1984, (3 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 20-22)
      - 1985-1987, (4 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 1-4)
      - Ballot Proofs, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - Nominations, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - 1989-1990, (2 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 7-8)
      - Nominations, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      - Nominations Process Review Committee, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - 1991-1993, (3 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 11-13)
      - 1988-1991 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Executive Director
      - Executive Director's Contract (Jack Healey), 1992-1993 (Box 5, Folder 15)
      - Healey, Jack--Article and AI Response, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 16)
      - Reports to the Board, 1984-1993 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Search Committee, 1981, 1993, (2 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 2-3)
    - Fundraising
      - London Meeting of Major Funding Sources, 1989 July (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Program Reviews, 1988-1993 (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - Miscellaneous, 1987-1991 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - General (Board Memoranda), 1988-1990 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - German Playboy Article Re: AI, September 1992 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Group Assessments Task Force, 1987-1993 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Homosexuality--Guidelines, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 10)
      (AIUSA Comments On)
    - Human Rights Covenants, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Information Services Program Review, 1992-1993 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - International Human Rights--Report of Task Force on, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - International Secretariat